<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Authors | Home</title>
    <link>/authors/</link>
      <atom:link href="/authors/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Authors</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>img/map[gravatar:%!s(bool=false) shape:circle]</url>
      <title>Authors</title>
      <link>/authors/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/authors/admin/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/authors/admin/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I graduated from the University of Notre Dame in May 2019 with a major in 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://acms.nd.edu/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Applied and Computational Mathematics and Statistics&lt;/a&gt;
 and a concentration in Biological Sciences. I have enjoyed math my entire life, but I never had much interest in studying pure math. Thanks to a handful of influential teachers, I became concerned about environmental problems while in high school; my undergraduate research with 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://biology.nd.edu/people/david-medvigy/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr. David Medvigy&lt;/a&gt;
 introduced me to the ways in which my academic interest could align with my calling to combat environmental problems. After graduating, I wanted to continue using my quantitative and computational skills to solve environmental problems, so I chose to continue my studies at the University of Washington, where I am currently a second-year graduate student studying 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://quantitative.uw.edu/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Quantitative Ecology and Resource Management&lt;/a&gt;
.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe that climate change is the most important problem facing society. However, I also aspire to solve problems that are human-centered. The COVID-19 pandemic has given me an interest in public health, and I am excited to research problems at the intersection of public health and climate change while working under 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://deohs.washington.edu/faculty/tania-m-busch-isaksen&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr. Tania Busch Isaksen&lt;/a&gt;
. For example, my thesis work is likely to investigate the relationship between extreme heat and mortality and explore how this relationship and climate change may interact in the coming decades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For fun, I enjoy running, watching sports (primarily NCAA football, but also the NBA and, to a lesser extent, the MLB and NFL), playing video games, and consuming superhero content. When I have the chance, I also love hiking!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Robert Ford</title>
      <link>/authors/robert-ford/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/authors/robert-ford/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
